<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A few words to Nath. Coleman's late epistle directed to be read in the assemblies of Gods people. Shewing the falseness and unsoundness of his doctrines therein contained. Presented unto the view and perusal of him, and them that are the encouragers and spreaders thereof, or any others, to whose hands they have come, with a copy of his own condemnation, &amp;c. Unto which is added, An answer to T. Crisp's sixth part of Babels Builders.</title>
            <author>Field, John, 1652-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F863B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215433</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827316</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827316</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1907:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A few words to Nath. Coleman's late epistle directed to be read in the assemblies of Gods people. Shewing the falseness and unsoundness of his doctrines therein contained. Presented unto the view and perusal of him, and them that are the encouragers and spreaders thereof, or any others, to whose hands they have come, with a copy of his own condemnation, &amp;c. Unto which is added, An answer to T. Crisp's sixth part of Babels Builders.</title>
                  <author>Field, John, 1652-1723.</author>
                  <author>Richardson, Richard, 1623?-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>By John Field. Signed at end: J.F.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Coleman, Nathaniel.  An epistle to be read in the assemblies; also included, a reply to: Crisp, Thomas. Sixth part of Babel's-builders unmaskt.</note>
                  <note>Includes paragraph after initials signed: Richard Richardson.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Coleman, Nathaniel. --  Epistle to be read in the assemblies.</term>
               <term>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent. --  Sixth part of Babel's-builders unmaskt.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31734:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31734:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Few Words TO <hi>Nath. Coleman's</hi> LATE EPISTLE, DIRECTED To be Read in the Aſſemblies of Gods People.</p>
            <p>Shewing the Falſeneſs and Unſoundneſs of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines therein contained.</p>
            <p>Preſented unto the View and Peruſal of him, and them that are the Encouragers and Spreaders thereof, or any others, to whoſe hands they have come, with a Copy of his own Condemnation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto which is added, An Anſwer to <hi>T. Criſp</hi>'s ſixth Part of <hi>Babels Builders.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 11.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For there muſt be Hereſies, among you, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt among you.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 1.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Beloved believe not every Spirit, but try the Spirits whether they be of God; becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out into the World.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>IT is a certain truth and experience dayly ſheweth that the troubles of the righteous are many and the exerciſes great and various, that from the birth of the fleſh, ſtock of <hi>Iſhmael</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:31734:2"/>and the Generation of envious and perſecuting <hi>Cain,</hi> they meet with all as <hi>cruel mockings, reproaches, afflictions, Spoile of Goods, yea moreover of Bonds and Impriſonments,</hi> though bleſſed be the Lord God through the aſſiſtance of his powerful and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirit, they are dayly ſtrengthened and enabled chearfully to endure, and go through the ſame, knowing in themſelves that they have in heaven a better and more endurable ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and they firmly believe that <hi>theſe light afflictions</hi> (for ſo they are comparatively) <hi>which is but for a moment worketh for them a more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory, while we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen, are Eternal.</hi> And the People and children of God in this our day and Age, have not been, neither are only exerciſed on this wiſe but as the Primitive Chriſtians were with falſe Brethren and teachers, and their corrupt Doctrin, which they endeavour both publickly and privately to bring in, <hi>whoſe pernitious ways ſome have followed, by reaſon of whom the way of truth hath been evil ſpoken of, but their Judgment doth not linger, neither doth their damnation ſlumber.</hi> And let none think theſe things ſtrange for this day is that fulfilled among us which the Apoſtles writ, to the Primitive believers, <hi>viz. Alſo of your own ſelves ſhall men ariſe ſpeaking perverſe things to draw away diſciples after them, therefore watch</hi> in the holy light <hi>for what is reproveable is firſt made manifeſt thereby,</hi> and as every one keeps thereto and walks therein, they will not by the feigned words of any, be made merchandize of, but will know, feel and witneſs to their comfortable fellowſhip with God and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is the very thing this evil Spirit that hath entered the corrupt teachers <hi>that from our ſelves have riſen (who bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction)</hi> ſeeks with feigned pretence to the light and Spirit of God, to draw people from t. The which in ſome meaſure the following lines will ſhew, and in love are writ for that end. And to detect the falſe Doctrin of one of theſe corrupt teachers, that in our age hath riſen, who may be truly ſaid to be as <hi>A well without water, and a cloud without rain, carried with every tempeſt, to whom the miſt of darkneſs I reſerved forever.</hi> Except unfeigned repentance is known.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:31734:2"/>
            <p>Here follows A Coppy of a Letter ſent to <hi>N. C.</hi> in which the following anſwer was incloſed.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Nathaniel Coleman.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe incloſed is ſent thee to peruſe, that thou maiſt ſee the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and falſe Doctrin thou haſt publiſhed in thy Epiſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in publick print under the pretence of a motion from God, and it's my intent to publiſh the Incloſed, except thou wilt condemn the falſe Doctrins in thy ſaid Epiſtle, and the Spirit by which thou was led to write and publiſh them as publickly as they are made, and call the ſaid Epiſtles in. I have as yet omitted in the incloſed one thing (among the reſt) which is in p. <hi>3</hi> where there ſpeaking of the Lord gathering his people from off all the barren mountains and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate bills of Imaginations (thou in Parentheſis ſaith <hi>(wherein they have been acting for him)</hi> now herein is manifeſt a great errour and notorious falſe Doctrin, ſuch that the blind Prieſt of the nation can ſcarce excced in blindneſs, darkneſs, and Ignorance. And <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> if in any place I have either miſtook, miſquoted, or miſrepreſented thy words otherwiſe then the ſenſe will bear, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thee to manifeſt it, though I can and do truly ſay I knew not in the leaſt tittle that I have ſo done, and let me have an anſwer from thee in <hi>1</hi> or <hi>2</hi> Weeks time, otherwiſe I intend to publiſh it as aforeſaid, and if I heare not from thee I may add the aforeſaid falſe Doctrin to the reſt, with ſome things more, for ought I at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent know; ſo with the words of the Spirit unto the Church of <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea</hi> I at preſent may conclude, deſiring thee to make a right application thereof, i.e. <hi>becauſe thou ſaiſt I am rich and encreaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with goods, and have need of nothing, and knowſt not that thou art wretched and miſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked, I councel thee to buy of me, gold tried in the fire, that thou maiſt be rich, and white rayment that thou maiſt be clothed, and that the ſhame of thy nakedneſs, do not appear, and anoint thy eyes with eye Salve that thou maiſt ſec.</hi> Rev. <hi>3.17.18.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thy Friend that truly wiſheth thee godly Sorrow, and unfeigned repentancce unto the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and amendment of thy faults. <hi>I. Field.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:31734:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>N. C.</hi> I have ſeen and peruſed an Epiſtle unto which thy name is ſubſcribed, which thou begins with this preſcription, <hi>viz. <hi>To be read in the Aſſemblies of Gods People.</hi>
               </hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Note, but who <hi>N. C.</hi> doſt thou account ſo, and by what name or denomination, are they diſtinguiſhed from others.</note> This is thy order and preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet in Poſtſcript p. 6. thou ſaiſt, <hi>they that ſow to the orders of other mens preſcribing ſhall reap a crop of corruption:</hi> And what <hi>Nathaniel</hi> muſt they reap that ſow to thy orders and preſcription, muſt not they reap a crop of corruption? I am ſatisfied if they ſow to that Spirit that thou waſt led and acted by, willfully to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Gods heavenly power in <hi>G. F.</hi> (who thou confeſſeſt God hath raiſed up to bean Elder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <note n="*" place="margin">See thy own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation—p.</note> They, yea all they, if repent not, will certainly reap a crop of corruption, or if they Sow to thy orders or preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that proceed from that Spirit that lead thee to oppoſe Gods heavenly power, though thou maiſt thou art moved of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) they'l reap <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> better; for <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> pretended, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Impudently, falſly and Impiouſly ſaid, the Lord ſaid unto me, <hi>Go up.</hi> §. But now to thy Epiſtle which thou begins, viz. <hi>To all the flock of God that are ſcattered abroad, I am moved of the Lord God to write, to warn them in his name.</hi> Here thou ſpeaks as great words, and pretends unto as high a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion as <hi>Rabſhckah</hi> did: And in this firſt p. thou doſt not only <hi>warn</hi> but counſel alſo, <hi>in the fear of the Lord God</hi> (as thou ſaiſt) <hi>to follow his requirings in every one, that</hi> (ſaiſt thou) <hi>by it you may be taught to do his will in all things you undertake, &amp;c.</hi> For (ſaiſt thou) <hi>yee are the Garden of God, and his Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, the ſheep of his fold, and flock of his Paſture, which he is feeding, with the bread of knowledg, &amp;c.—therefore follow yea him in all his requirings, &amp;c.—that you may have right unto the tree of Life, which is in the midſt of the Garden of God. And may enter through the Gates into the City of our God, &amp;c.</hi> and in p. 3. thou ſaiſt <hi>Sion is the City of their Solemnity where Salvation is known for walls and bulworks, &amp;c.</hi>—and yet in p. 4. Thou exhorts or councels, the flock of God (to whom thou pretends a motion from God to write) <hi>to believe in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31734:3"/>the light, that they may be the Children of it;</hi> come <hi>Nat. C</hi> Let's expoſtulate this matter, are them that are <hi>the Children of God, his Husbandry, the ſheep of his fold and flock of his Paſture, &amp;c.</hi> Still in the unbelief, and darkneſs? (which is the way of the wicked) that thou exhorts them, to believe in the light, that they <hi>May</hi> be the Children of it. What Doctrin is here? (as applyed unto the flock of God and Citizens of Sion) the Citty of the Saints Solemnity where ſalvation is known for walls and Bulworks; and yet theſe thou ſaiſt thou art <hi>moved of God to warn and councel, &amp;c.</hi> And exhorts them to believe in the light, that they may be the Children of it; what <hi>Nat.</hi> Are the flock <hi>and Garden of God Citizens of Sion, who have ſalvation for walls and Bullworks,</hi> Children of darkneſs? that thou pretends a <hi>motion from God</hi> to exhort them <hi>to believe in the light that they may be the Children of it?</hi> [mark] the words <hi>may be</hi> clearly Imply they are not yet, tho in contradiction hereunto thou in the ſame page ſaith, <hi>God hath called them <hi>out of darkneſs into his marbelous light,</hi>
               </hi> and alſo tells them of <hi>returning unto Sion, with the redeemed, with Songs and everlaſting Joy upon their heads, and here ſaiſt thou ſorrow and mourning fleeth away, which was <hi>in the night</hi> when Wee were <hi>in darkneſs;</hi>
               </hi> then it ſeems theſe are in the light, and their Sorrow and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which was in the <hi>night</hi> is fled away, and thoy return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto Sion, with Songs of everlaſting Joy upon their heads, and are partakers of Gods Salvation, and children of the light, yea ſuch, that do already, not only believe in Chriſt the light, but alſo walk in it (as all the Nations of them that are ſaved ſhall) and ſo are the Children of it; yet after all this thou exhorts them (who thou telleſt are come to the high States aforeſaid <hi>to believe in the light that they <hi>may be</hi> the Children of it;</hi> Oh what confuſion is here. But to proceed thou ſaiſt to the flock of Gods Paſture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that God is feeding them with the bread of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, prethee <hi>N. C.</hi> let's have<note n="*" place="margin">And not out of <hi>Will Regers</hi> book, for that will not paſs with the Children of light.</note>Scripture to pròve this new doctrin by, <hi>that God is feeding his flock (or People) with the bread of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> Chriſt who is the ſhepherd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31734:4"/>of his flock, ſaith, <hi>I am the bread of life; he that cometh unto me, ſhall never hunger, and he that believeth me ſhall never thirſt. Alſo Gods command unto Adam</hi> was, that he ſhould not cat of the tree of knowledg, therefore let's have expreſs Scripture as <hi>F. Bugg</hi> ſaith, to prove that God is feeding his People with the bread of knowledg, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again thou goeſt on as aforeſaid, and exhorts the People, whom thou ſaiſt are <hi>Gods flock and Garden to follow him, &amp;c.</hi> that they <hi>may have right, to the tree of life, which is in the midſt of the Garden of God &amp;c.</hi> What <hi>Nat.</hi> are not they that are the flock of his Paſture entered through the gates into the City of our God, and yet p. 3. thou ſaiſt <hi>Sion is the City of our ſolemnity, where Salvation is known for</hi> walls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then furely they are in it that truly ſo know it. And further, if Gods People are his <hi>Garden,</hi> and the tree of life be in the midſt of the Garden, certainly they have a right thereto that have gotten within the gates. Oh <hi>Nat.</hi> art not thou a weak man to meddle with ſuch things, which it appears thou doſt not underſtand, and is it not paſt doubt? yea ſurely it is, that thou didſt not wait low in the counſel of the Lord God for wiſdom, when thou writ this Epiſtle and Poſtſcript. And therefore is it, ſo confuſed, and void of true wiſdom, but without all doubt, thou waſt in the ſame Spirit thou was led by <hi>to oppoſe Gods heavenly power in</hi> G. F. <hi>when he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing Friends to have womens meetings</hi> (as thou haſt confeſt) And in that Spirit haſt thou writ this Epiſtle and Poſtſcript. And therefore I do adviſe thee to do as thou ſaiſt, thou then didſt, <hi>viz. confeſs thy Errours</hi> (call in thy Epiſtle) <hi>and truly humble thy ſelf before the Lord and ſeek him with tears,</hi> for certainly thou haſt now as great reaſon, as then thou hadſt, leaſt as thou ſaiſt, <hi>the lord cut thee off in his fury, for there is none can deliver out of his hand.</hi> And if thy doctrin in the 3. p. be true, ſure thy ſtate is bad, for there ſpeaking of the fear of God, and hell fire, (thou adds) <hi>where the worm never dieth, nor the fire of Gods Indignation, never goeth out, but remains <hi>for ever</hi> upon the minds of them that diſobey the truth, which is the <hi>Earneſt</hi> of their everlaſting miſery, that is their portion <hi>for ever.</hi>
               </hi> What no place for repentance, nor no other provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion if any ſhould be prevailed upon, to diſobey the truth,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31734:4"/>through the ſubtile workings of him that lies in wait to deceive, and for want of watching in, and keeping to the light, is there no way for their Reſtoration, muſt the <hi>fire of Gods Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on remain <hi>for ever upon their minds,</hi> muſt that be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> earneſt and portion <hi>for ever,</hi>
               </hi> will not patient ſubmitting unto his Righteous Judgments and correcting hand obtain no relief from him who delights in mercy, neither that Faith that he is the Author of, by which not only the mouths of Lyons, hath been ſtopt, but the violence of fire quenched, procure no relief? What Scripture haſt thou to prove this new Doctrin by? Oh <hi>N. C.</hi> Conſider of thy unſcriptural and unſound Doctrine which thou haſt delivered under pretence <hi>of a moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from God, &amp;c.</hi> And repent for thy taking his name in vain, and no more intitle, (the Immaginations of thy heart and brain) with or to <hi>the motion or Counſel of God,</hi> neither ſay, <hi>he requires theſe things at thy hands, nor lays them upon thee, though in</hi> p. 2. thou ſaiſt. <hi>Theſe things lay upon me from God &amp;c.</hi> And thou writes thus. <hi>My glory (ſaith the Lord God will not I give unto another, but will put a hook into the Noſtrils of all that go from him. &amp;c, into any Imaginations, &amp;c.</hi> And in the ſame page thou ſaiſt as <hi>you act for him</hi> (i. e. God) <hi>you will reach Gods witneſs in all Conſciences.</hi> Now I do declare thy Epiſtle, and Doctrin therein doth not reach, (nor anſwer to Gods witneſs in my Conſcience, nor in his faithſul Peoples; But contrary wiſe, I teſtify that the witneſs (or Spirit of the pure unchangeable God in me) I do find to raiſe a Teſtimony in my heart againſt not only thy Epiſtle and Doctrin therein but the Spirit, by which thou waſt led to write it, not to be of God; but the ſame that in many Ages under the pretence and mask of truth, and with ſome of the words of it would draw People from the Truth and True foundation <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and the order of his Goſpel of peace, life and Salvation, into ranting Airy notions, vain Imaginations and confuſion. And conſider how thou, <hi>(N. C.)</hi> haſt ſaid that <hi>God will put a hook into the Noſtrils of any that go from him into any Imaginations, &amp;c.</hi> Oh <hi>N. C.</hi> that there might be (if it be the will of God) an Eye open'd in thee, and kept open by the power of the Lord whereby thou mighteſt ſee what Imaginations thou haſt run into, and new Doctrines thou under pretence <hi>of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31734:5"/>from God</hi> (which greatly aggravates thy crime) hath brought forth and publiſhed to the world, ſome of which I have in brief hinted at, and may give thee a hint of more §. 2. Thou ſaiſt ſpeaking to thy dear friends and Brethren, <hi>This is to put you in mind, how graciouſly God hath dealt, and is dealing with his People, &amp;c.—In leading them out of Egypts land, &amp;c.—That in this our Journey none may be drawn out, from the Guide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of God's good Spirit within them, to joyn to any form of like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or appearance though never ſo beautiful but as you are led by the Pillar of the Cloud by day, and the Pillar of fire by night, which ſhines in all your hearts and Conſciences, &amp;c.</hi> Come <hi>Nat.</hi> Let me have Scripture to prove, that that Pillar of the Cloud by day, and that Pillar of fire by night (which went before old <hi>Iſrael</hi>) <hi>ſhines in all Gods peoples hearts and Conſciences,</hi> in this day of the Lords inward and ſpiritual appearance, in the hearts and Conſciences of his People, by his divine light, holy Spirit and grace in his new Covenant; for, was not that day and night there ſpoken of outward; and that Pillar, and cloud which old <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaw viſible unto the outward eye: but if thou meaneſt that the light or Spirit of Chriſt, <hi>is that Pillar of Clond by Day, and Pillnr of fire by night, which ſhines in all his Peoples hearts;</hi> let's have a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to prove this new Doctrin. Again, in poſtſcript, p. 6. thou ſpeaking of the knowledg of God, ſaith, <hi>for want of that the People periſht in all generations.</hi>—Now I will grant that this complaint, was made by the Lord through his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>i.e.</hi> my People are deſtroyed for lack of knowledg; but it was under that diſpenſation, wherein the Prieſts lips ſhould keep the Peoples knowledg, and when the Prieſts had reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed knowledg and forgot the law of God; ſee <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I deſire thee to conſider whether many in our day and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, have and do not periſh, not for want of knowledg, but for want of obedience to what they did know; for doth not God by his divine light, Spirit and grace, which he enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens all with, which he pours upon all, and appears to all, (<hi>and not by that Pillar old</hi> Iſrael <hi>followed, and beheld with their viſible eyes</hi>) ſo far ſhine into all mens hearts as to ſhew them what is good, and what he requires at their hands? And if ſo (as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thou wilt not deny) what thinkeſt thou if theſe men (that have this knowledg given them of God, and yet for want of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31734:5"/>doing good and what the Lord requires at their hands) ſhould periſh will it be for want of knowledg, or want of obedience? Oh! <hi>N. C.</hi> Conſider whilſt thou haſt time, what god moved thee to publiſh this Doctrin; ſurely, it was the god of this world, the Prince of the power of the Air, the Spirit that works in the hearts of the Children of diſobedience, that moved led and guided thee to write theſe Airy imaginations and falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Doctrines, and deludedly to father them upon God, and not the Spirit of the pure God, therefore repent of them call them in, and condemn that Spirit now (as formerly) and that Spirit that hath led thee to write and publiſh them, leſt thy own Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, p. 6. <hi>of periſhing from the knowledge of God</hi> become thy portion, for thou certainly haſt gone into the practice or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that which by the guidance of his Spirit thou waſt not led into, in publiſhing theſe unſound or falſe Doctrines in the name of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I further obſerve in thy 6. p. thou ſaiſt, <hi>they that ſow to the fleſh, or orders of other mens pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing, ſhall certainly reap a crop of Corruption.</hi> This thou writes unto the flock of God. And what meaneſt thou by <hi>other mens preſcribing?</hi> doſt mean; <hi>they may ſow to the fleſh, or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of their own, or</hi> own <hi>mens preſcribing,</hi> and not to other mens? explain this alſo let's know what <hi>thoſe mens orders are that ſome among the flock of God,</hi> which (as thou ſaiſt,) <hi>have turned from the truth and way of the Lord, and committed abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in following.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come let's have a Catalogue of <hi>theſe mens orders,</hi> and let's know whether any of the flock of God gave them forth, for here hath been a great cry and noiſe againſt orders, <hi>(Comely orders) modes, forms, ceremonies, times of prayer, without diſtinction, outward gatherings, Church-fellowſhip, external memberſhip,</hi> witneſs a book call'd, <hi>bright ſhining light,</hi> by <hi>Phil. Ang.</hi> before thine came publick by looſe ranting Spirits, ſuch who <hi>dwell in the land of darkneſs, <hi>that is without any order,</hi> Job.</hi> 10.22. And I would have thee examine whether thou art an inhabitant in that land, &amp; under the rule &amp; government of him that is Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; or under Chriſt's government of the increaſe of whoſe government and peace the Prophet ſaid, <hi>There ſhall be no end, upon the throne of David, and upon his kingdom, to <hi>order it,</hi> and to eſtabliſh it, with judgment, and with juſtice from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31734:6"/>even for ever. The zeal of the Lord of Hoſts will perform this.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>God was the God of order, and not of confuſion in all the Churches of the Saints.</hi> And he gave order to the Churches, ſee, <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1. he alſo rejoyced in their order that truth had led them into) ſaying to the Saints at <hi>Coloſs, for though I be abſent in the fleſh, yet I am with you in the ſpirit joying, and beholding your order, and ſtedfaſtneſs of your faith in Chriſt.</hi> Alſo in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and laſt he tells the Believers, after he had reprehended them for ſeveral diſorders, that the reſt will I ſet in <hi>order</hi> when I come, by which it appears that <hi>Paul</hi> that man of God was for <hi>order,</hi> and left <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Crete</hi> to ſet in <hi>order</hi> the things that were wanting among the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers. And what doſt think, <hi>N. C.</hi> that thoſe things, that were ſet in <hi>order</hi> amongſt the believers by this man of God, was a ſeed of Corruption, ſown by him, and a crop of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption reaped by them? if thou ſo believeſt thou art to be pitied for thy ignorance. And I query whether thou believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, by the ſame Spirit of God ſome among the Children of light in our Age, have not been made inſtrumental to ſet in order ſome things, that were wanting among the believers in the light of Chriſt within; yea or nay. And come <hi>N C.</hi> let me, and all whoſe hands thy Epiſtle hath come to, know, what orders theſe are, that have proved ſo ſatal as to the flock of God, and who they are that have followed them as aforeſaid, alſo who made theſe <hi>orders,</hi> that ſo knowing both, the makers and the <hi>orders,</hi> we may be capable to judge; for to cry againſt <hi>Orders, Orders, Orders,</hi> and not tell what <hi>Orders</hi> is, but like mens beating the Air, ſtrikeing at their ſhaddows, or quarelling with their own imaginations, or like the clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous woman, that pulls down her houſe with her hands. So having hinted at ſome of thy new Doctrines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and given thee the judgment of Truth, both upon thy Epiſtle and Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, (and the ſpirit thou writ them in) I ſhall at preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, and in plainneſs tell thee, that they ſurely were thy true friends, in the judgment of Truth, <hi>that ſtopt thy Epiſtle from coming out ſooner,</hi> though thou defireſt the Lord may not lay it to their charge, for it's come ſoon enough, to manifeſt, thy weakneſs if not wickedneſs (to deliver ſuch things in the name of the Lord, and expoſe them in publick, and direct
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31734:6"/>them to the flock of God, and to be read in the Aſſemblies of Gods People;) but bleſſed be God; who hath given that good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding unto his People, that live in his holy fear, that they try Spirits and not receive, nor have unity with, nor ſuffer (except impoſed upon,) the reading of thoſe things in their Meetings, that proceed not from that Spirit and power, in which their unity and fellowſhip ſtands, tho to their grief and exerciſe they too often have (in their Meetings) the forced Teſtimonies or ſpeeches of ſome ſuch as <hi>N. C.</hi> impoſed upon them that they have not unity with, who are unruly and vain talkers, whoſe mouths, I believe, the Lord in his due time will ſtop.</p>
            <p>I am thy Friend that have ſhewed, or endeavourjd to ſhew thee thy miſtake and errours, that thou maiſt not go on in the fault which thou art overtaken in, in falſly pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ending a motion from God; therefore hear what <hi>John Pennyman</hi> ſaith in his book of Letters Printed in, 1680. <hi>viz. That it is the greateſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my or forgery under heaven, to ſay things in the name of the Lord, or that they are moved of the Lord, to ſpeak or do, and are not. Tho he can, like thee, cry againſt <hi>order</hi> and <hi>forms,</hi>
               </hi> yea the very <hi>form of ſound words</hi> (which the Apoſtle exhorted to) <hi>(i. e) <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thou</hi>
               </hi> in the aforſaid book in his letter to <hi>G. F.</hi> ſays, <hi>Away with your ſet form of words, of <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thou;</hi>
               </hi> tho (to manifeſt that he allows himſelf in that he condemns in others) he uſes them in the ſaid Letter to <hi>G. F.</hi> about 20. times. This I have hinted at, to ſhew the confuſion of him that hath cryed againſt orders, as <hi>T. Criſp,</hi> thee, and many others have, as alſo that thou mighteſt read his ſentence againſt ſuch as ſpeak things in the name of the Lord and as moved by him and are not,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Field. Jun.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THere is one paſſage or two more, that I may take a little notice of as p. 2. <hi>N. C.</hi> faith, <hi>The kingdom of God cometh not in outward obſervations, but is felt and known within, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all gather in from that, that would draw out the mind from God, to obſerve days, or times, or months, or years, concerning any matter or buſineſs, but as you are inwardly drawn or required by the Truth in your own particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:31734:7"/>
            <p>What then may the flock and People of God, (to whom thou ſaiſt thou art moved of God to write) have their minds by the Truth in their own particulars, inwardly drawn from God to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Days, Times, Months, and years, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What ſtrange, confuſed, <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> ranting Doctrin is here delivered (or aſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) that the <hi>Truth</hi> (of which there is no lye, and and in which here is no contradiction) may draw God's People's minds of from him who is the God of Truth. Oh the Lord if it be his will, open thy eyes that thou maiſt ſee thy groſs errour, and give thee a heart to repent of the ſame before it's too late. And now from hence alſo obſerve, he counſels or warns the flock of God all togather in from that that would draw out the mind from God, <hi>to obſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, or times, or months, or years, concerning any matter oribuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> but as you are inwardly drawn or required by the Truth, in your own particulars, by which he plainly grants, that the flock of God may be drawn or required by the truth in their own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, to obſerve days, or times, or months, or years. Now let <hi>N. C.</hi> ſhew what thoſe days, times, months, and years are, that he would not have them obſerve; alſo what days, times, months, and years, they may be required by the Truth in their own particulars to obſerve, for his Brother <hi>F. Bugg</hi> in his ungodly Book, makes a great cry, and calling for expreſs ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for meeting once amonth, at the tenth hour of the day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again in p. 4. ſpeaking to thy dear Friends and Brethren, <hi>&amp;c. That God</hi> (ſaiſt thou) <hi>hath viſited with a high hand,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that in this your Journey, none may be drawn out from the guidance of Gods good Spirit within them, to joyn to any form or likeneſs, or apparance. although never ſo beautiful, but as you are led by the Pillar of the Cloud by day, and the Pillar of fire by night—which guideth the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of the flock of his Companions out of all tranſgreſſion and Rebellion, &amp;c.</hi> Come let's examine this new Doctrin and ſee whether this man, while he would ſeem to be knowing and wiſe, is not become a fool and a novice, thus to preach up the Pillar of the Cloud, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To lead out of all tranſgreſſion, (which is the work of Chriſt in this Goſpel day, And pretend <hi>a motion from God, to warn and counſel his flock that none be drawn out from the guidance of God's good Spirit within them, to joyn to any form or likeneſs or appearance.</hi> Oh! <hi>Nat.</hi> I think thou haſt too much followed this counſel of <hi>not joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto any form,</hi> that thou haſt not kept <hi>the form of ſome words</hi> which the Apoſtle (that was truly moved of God) exhorted to,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31734:7"/>but thou pre tends <hi>a motion from God to warn and councel Gods flock not to joyn to any form,</hi> which though the Apoſtle exhorted to turn from them that had the form of Godlineſs, and not the power, yet I never read he exhorted the ſaints or flock of God not to joyn <hi>to any form,</hi> but contrary wiſe <hi>he thanked</hi> (that the <hi>Romans</hi>) <hi>had obey'd from the heart that form of Doctrin delivered unto them;</hi> ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. And obſerve after thou haſt <hi>exhorted or councel'd the flock of God not to be drawn from the guidance of God's good Spirit within them, to joyn to any form likeneſs or appearance, &amp;c.</hi> thou comes with a <hi>
                  <hi>but</hi> as you are led by the Pillar of fire by night, and the Pillar of a cloud by day.</hi> What then may they by this Pillar be drawn from the guidance of Gods good ſpirit within them into a form likeneſs and appearance; pray was not the Pillar of fire an appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? and doth appearance draw into appearance? What new ſtrange confuſed Doctrine is here, to drop from the pen of one <hi>moved of God</hi> to warn and couſel his flock, (as he ſaith) but the confuſion thereof ſhews it's not of God, <hi>for he is not the Author of confuſion.</hi> And thou ſeems to make the Spirit of God, and the Pillar of fire by night, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> two different things where thou coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels or exhorts, ſaying <hi>that none may be drawn out from the Guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Gods good Spirit with in them, to joyn to any form, likeneſs or appearance;</hi> [mark] but <hi>as you are led by the Pillar of a Cloud by day, and the Pillar of fire by night. Nat.</hi> Doſt thou believe that this <hi>Pillar of fire by night</hi> doth or will lead from the Spirit of God within, into forms, likeneſs and appearances; if thou ſo believeſt, how dareſt thou ſo commend this to the flock of God for a leader and guide is not this like preaching another Goſpel? then that which the Apoſtles preached, for if it lead from the Spirit of God within into forms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſure thoſe forms likeneſſes or appearances cannot be good: but why doſt thou direct or councel the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Sons (or Citizens) of Sion, who are comparable to fine God, to follow the Pillar of fire by night, for the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid unto the Saints in light. Yea are all Children of the light, and of the day; ye are not of the night nor of darkneſs. And <hi>John</hi> ſaid unto ſuch, <hi>the darkneſs is paſt, and the true light now ſhineth,</hi> and were not the Saint in light <hi>tranſlated out of the kingdom of darkneſs, into the kingdom of his dear Son;</hi> and we do not read of <hi>a Pillar of fire by night</hi> in this Kingdom: for out of Sion the perfection of beauty God doth ſhine; and Chriſt reigns, in new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> where there is no night, <hi>but the glory of God did lighten it, and the lamb
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31734:8"/>is the light thereof, and the gates ſtand open by day, and there is no night;</hi> ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23.24. Therefore conſider <hi>Nat.</hi> whether herein, thou haſt not darkned counſel by uttering words without divine knowledge, (tho thou pretends thou waſt moved of God to counſel his flock,) and alſo ſaiſt, God is feeding his People with the bread of knowledge. But if thee means <hi>by this Pillar of fire, &amp;c.</hi> The Spirit of God or light of Chriſt, (becauſe thou ſaiſt, <hi>it ſhines in all their hearts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and guides out af <hi>all</hi> tranſgreſſion,</hi>) then thy doctrin is thus. <hi>That the flock of God muſt not be drawn from the guidance of God's good Spirit within, &amp;c.</hi> But as they are <hi>led by his good Spirit within</hi> (or the light that ſhines in all their Conſciences) what is this but Ranteriſm, or Blaſphemy, to rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the Spirit to contradict the Spirit. And yet this is (the more the pity) the abſurdity confuſion and Ranteriſm, that Spirit that hath entered and beguiled <hi>N. C.</hi> (and too to many) leads into, tho they pretend unto and highly preach up in words, the light and Spirit of God, yet they are as certainly (in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) gone out of the unity and fellowſhip thereof, and from the guidance of the ſame, as them that run and God never ſent them, and in the Spirit they are now in, can no more profit the People, then thoſe in that day did. The Lord God Almighty, who hath opened the ear in his People that can truly try words as the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat taſteth meat, keep it open and grant, that they may never lend an ear unto any but the true Shepherds voice, that the ſheep of his fold, and flock of his Paſture them may be, and know <hi>Jeſus</hi> to put them forth (of all that's contrary unto his mind and Teſtimony) and give unto them Eternal life, that in life and peace, and the word of God's patience, they may poſſeſs their ſouls, and not regard them that may ſeem to be ſomewhat; but add no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, unto the refreſhing of them that are truly born of God. And ſuch like, there were in the Apoſtles days, who were vain talkers and puffed up in their minds, concerning whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaid, he would not know the Speech of them but the power; but ſome that cannot truly diſcern between things that differ, may be liable, if they keep not their minds unto the Lord, and live in his fear) to be beguiled by the feigned words, and fine ſpeeches of them that are out of the unity and life of Truth, and in a Spirit that would cauſe the offence of the croſs to ceaſe, and give liberty under the profeſſion of the truth, to pay Tythes, Marry by a Prieſt, ſay you to a ſingle perſon, cry againſt forms,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31734:8"/>yet run into and plead for ſwearing and the form thereof, as one of <hi>T. Criſps's.</hi> company lately hath, by which it's clearly manifeſt what Spirit they are guided by, brings forth and leads into, and yet theſe will plead for the Chriſtian Quaker, and falſly pretend unto the Truth as it was in the beginning. </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="condemnation">
            <head>The Copy of <hi>N. C's.</hi> Condemnation.</head>
            <p>I <hi>N. C.</hi> The laſt ſummer hearing that <hi>George Fox</hi> through divers Countys had encouraged the ſetting up of Womens Meetings, and that he intended to come into <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> and not having a clear underſtanding in the work of Reſtoration in which Women are meet helps to the men, did ſecretly deſire of the Lord that he would ſhew me whether the thing was well pleaſing to him, but I not waiting low in the Counſel of the Lord God for wiſdom to do his will, being at a Meeting at <hi>Shattenford</hi> where <hi>George Fox</hi> was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to adviſe the ſetting up a Womans-Meeting in this County; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent for before the Meeting, did with ſome other Friends, reaſon with <hi>G. F.</hi> and oppoſed him very much, ſhewing, as I thought, by the Scripture that the man was the lord, and the woman was to be ſubject to him, but he ſhewed that in Chriſt, the male and female are all one, and that they are meet helps, in the Reſtoration. After the Meeting, many Friends being call'd together, we did open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſe him, altho he often warned me to take heed, yet I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully oppoſe him untill the fire of the Lord did burn within me, and I ſaw the Angel of the Lord, with his ſword drawn in his hand, ready to cut me off. At which I was afraid, and durſt not depart before I did confeſs my errour before Friends, becauſe I had oppoſed God's heavenly power, in him who raiſed him up, to be an Elder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, for which tranſgreſſion, I did truly humble my ſelf before the Lord, and ſought him with tears, whoſe power reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto me, which cauſed me to cry out in ſecret, <hi>Lord, what is man that thou ſhouldeſt be mindful of him; or the ſon of man, that thou ſhouldeſt thus viſit him inthy love, and in tender mercy.</hi> Now Friends the Lord having reſtored me again unto his truth, in which I feel a dayly encreaſe of peace, and life from him, for which I do from the bottom of my heart render living praiſes and thankſgiving to him, who is God over all, worthy to be feared and magnified for ever.</p>
            <p>This is writ as a <hi>warning</hi> to all friends, that they may not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Lords heavenly power, nor endeavour to ſtop his work which he is carrying on againſt all oppoſers; leſt the Lord cut you off in his ſury; for there is none that can deliver out of his hand</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:31734:9"/>
            <p>This is a true Coppy, and hath been proved by the original of his own hand writing, and may ſerve to ſhew that he is one of them men that are given to change, and that proves the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaying true, that <hi>the double minded man is unſtable in all his ways, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let him take the good Counſel of the ſaid Apoſtle,</hi> 4 Cap. 8 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c. Cleanſe your hands ye ſinners, and purifie your heart ye double minded, be afflicted and mourn, and weep; let your laughter be turned into mourning, and your joy into heavineſs: humble your ſelves in the ſight of the Lord, and he ſhall lift you up.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>
               <hi>Thomas Criſp</hi> the Author of the ſixth Part of <hi>Babel Builders,</hi> &amp;c. Proved a Babler, and a fooliſh feeble Contender for the Book falſly ſtiled, <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>How forcible are right words! but what doth your arguing reprove?</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Job 6.25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>Surely the Serpent will bite without Enchantment, and a Babler is no better; the beginning of the words of his Mouth is foolliſhneſs: and the end of his talk is miſchievous madneſs,</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſ. 10.11, 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN his firſt Page, line 2. he ſpeaks of my <hi>Rapſadoe,</hi> I ſuppoſe he means Rapſody or Rhapſody (which is a fit name for his <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi>) ſignifying a confuſed Collection; and what else can any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of a <hi>Babel-Builder</hi> but confuſion. But I find the man's offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed becauſe I ſaid in my reply, unto his 5 <hi>Babel. p.</hi> 5. <hi>I queſtion whether all the paper I have writ will hold them all? viz.</hi> his lyes, Slanders, Nicknames, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which <hi>T. C.</hi> Reply'd, <hi>It muſt be a great many to ſtuff two Sheets and a half.</hi> Anſwer, a great many no doubt they are, (and them that read and rightly underſtand thy <hi>Babels,</hi> may ſee it, but I had not when in the 5 p. writ two Sheets and a half) therefore think not to excuſe thy ſelf for writing <hi>untruths</hi> by falſly ſaying. It's my fault, for it's he, <hi>viz.</hi> The Devil that is out, of the truth, and in whom there is no truth, that leads thee, and all them that write and ſpeak untruths (or lies) ſo to do, of which my deſire is thou mayſt heartily repent. But thou ſaiſt in thy I p. Over and over <hi>I find none</hi> (i. e.) Lyes <hi>proved againſt me</hi>) which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31734:9"/>makes me think of the Proverb, <hi>(Who is more blind then they that will not ſee)</hi> only <hi>I. F.</hi> ſays, I <hi>tell thee, or I deny, or I affirm, and ſometimes by queries are not,</hi> &amp;c. Anſwer <hi>Thomas.</hi> w'ont this ſerve for proofs? if not, why didſt not thou produce ſtronger againſt me and Friends? for thou conceitedly ſaiſt, <hi>I have proved, I ſay, I deny,</hi> above twenty times in thy laſt Sheet, (as if thou thought to be heard for thy much Babling) and then fooliſhly quotes thy own confuſed <hi>Babels, &amp;c.</hi> for thy authority, ſee thy 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7, 8, pages, but if thy Say-ſo's be no proof, as indeed it's not, then thy work is yet to do, thy proofs to make, and thy labour in 6 <hi>Babels</hi> and all thy babling in vain. But <hi>perhaps</hi> thou maiſt anſwer as in thy 5 <hi>Babel</hi> p. 13. <hi>But in caſe I had ſo ſaid, it doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low I muſt ſo do.</hi> No <hi>Tho.</hi> Informers againſt Chriſtian Preachers little regard what they ſay. And though thou ſaiſt, <hi>I have proved, &amp;c.</hi> It doth not follow thou haſt ſo done, therefore hear what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid, <hi>Anſwer a fool according to his folly, leſt he be wiſe in his own conceit.</hi> And that thy pretended proofs may be manifeſt to be but meer <hi>thinkſo's</hi> and <hi>ſayſo's</hi> take one ſample of them as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, in the 13 p. of my reply unto thy 5 <hi>Babel,</hi> I quoted theſe words of thine, <hi>viz. But one reaſon why I paid that ſo often montioned as Tythes, was as a witneſs, that I was not taught my fear, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of G. F. &amp;c. Nor receive his traditions for Doctrines, and that I had not ſacrificed all my faith, conſcience and judgment to his orders, your Idol to Worſhip, that as too many both ſmall and great do. But as a Teſtimony againſt your impoſition, &amp;c.</hi> Thus far <hi>T. C.</hi> to which I reply'd he takes no notice, that I call'd upon him (and now do again) to <hi>prove <hi>any of the many both ſmall and great, that ſo do,</hi>
               </hi> to which in 6 <hi>Babel,</hi> 8 p. <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaith, <hi>I. F.</hi> ſay's of me, page. 13. <hi>He takes no notice that I call'd upon him, to prove any of the many; but that is falſe, for in, p.</hi> 11. <hi>I ſay thus, that he bid me prove any,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I ſay (ſaith T. C.) <hi>I think</hi> himſelf and</hi> R. R. <hi>have ſo done—and theſe be too many. And then he adds, now how dareſt thou affirm ſuch an untruth as</hi> to ſay I take no notice, <hi>of that? when as I particularly anſwer to both any and many.</hi> Thus far <hi>T. C.</hi> Anſwer obſerve firſt, how <hi>T. C.</hi> proves that <hi>any of the many,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Do ſarcafice <hi>all their Faith,</hi> Conſcience and judgment to G. F's</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, their Idol to worſhip? Why how doth he prove it? How thus he ſays (in 5 <hi>Babel.</hi> p. 11. and in his 6 <hi>Babel.</hi> p. 8.) <hi>I think <hi>himſelf, and</hi>
               </hi> R. R <hi>have ſo done.</hi> Pray mind his pre tended proof is but a meer and baſe <hi>thinkſo.</hi> 2. Let the Reader in truth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31734:10"/>Judge where and in whom the falſity and untruth is that <hi>T. C.</hi> queries how <hi>J. F.</hi> dare affirm. And 3. What validity his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended proofs are of, (that he braggs ſo much of.) And he ſeems by his ſaying <hi>how dare J F. &amp;c.</hi> to make as if it were ſome heinous crime, to ſay <hi>T. C. <hi>think'ſo</hi>
               </hi> is no proof, of his wicked falſe lying and ſlanderous charge aforeſaid againſt <hi>too many both ſmall and great, Sacraficing <hi>all their faith, Conſcience and judgment</hi> to G. F's. <hi>orders</hi>
               </hi> (which note, though greatly cry'd againſt, we could never get a Coppy of thoſe he ſcoffinglycalls <hi>G.F's</hi> orders, tho we have often call'd for them) ſo by this his falſe charge &amp; <hi>thinkſo</hi> he in his great folly and enmity doth render me and <hi>R. R.</hi> with an <hi>&amp; cetera,</hi> void of all Faith Conſcience and Judgment. And this I have inſtanced as a ſample of his proofs as aforeſaid, of which he ſo often conceitedly ſaith <hi>I have proved,</hi> when indeed upon exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation it appears but <hi>ſuch an one</hi> (<hi>T. C.</hi> Words) as <hi>T. C's</hi> bare empty, miſtaken <hi>thinkſo;</hi> I might give more inſtances, but this is enough. And as for his lying, Take this one proof for brevity ſake, to wit his inſerting under his hand in publick print, that <hi>G. F. Will not admit, that any have the leaſt meaſure of the Spirit, that ſubmit not unto his Laws,</hi> as he ſcornfully calls them; ſee the 10 page, and 4, <hi>Babel.</hi> (this needs no comments) and I might ſpend ſo much time and paper to give a Catalogue of thy lies, falſhoods, and flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and nicknames, which are not a few; but thou haſt not clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy ſelf of them I have already charged upon thee, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thy pretences, therefore let thy own wickedneſs correct thee, for the day is come and coming in which thy folly is and ſhall be manifeſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for in the light thou art ſeen to be of the number of them men of corrupt minds, that reſiſt the truth (who ſaid the Apoſtles concerning the Faith are reprobates. And now take ſome, (&amp; but ſome) of the many names thou call'ſtime &amp; <hi>R. R. G. W. &amp;c.</hi> which are as followeth, &amp; may ſerve to manifeſt what Spirit thou art of; <hi>Mercinary Reformado, Itiſſ;—, Cheat, Drudge, Arrogant Prater, proud Boaſter, Inquiſitor to the Bull and Mouth, Inquiſition Officer, Black-fryer-like fellow, like a lazy begging fryer, falſe accuſer, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lyars, he <hi>(i. e.) J. F.</hi> May have an eye to an Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or Informers place, of the Synagogue of Satan, ſuch that</hi> Paul <hi>fought with at</hi> Epheſus, <hi>that abominable</hi> R. Richardſon, <hi>Swiniſh belly, like vermin.</hi> And page 11, he hath the term <hi>Pick pocket, again that abominable and arrogant</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:31734:10"/>G. W. For that is the manner of ſome <hi>Billingſgate.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me ſuch is thy enmity, that in 13. p. 5 <hi>Babel.</hi> thou ſaiſt <hi>thou can't defame me,</hi> but know <hi>he that hideth hatred with lying lips, and he that uttereth a ſlander, is a fool.</hi> And if this was as true (as it's notoriouſly falſe) that I am ſo bad, as I cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed, why didſt not thou make proof thereof, and ſhew who I had wronged, overreached, or cheated, for I call'd upon thee in my laſt or to ſhew who I had cheated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As aforeſaid, or ever had any thing of, directly or indirectly, but what I came honeſtly by or laboured for, and Not by begging or cheating, Gifts, or Rewards. And I then proffered for every SUCH Farthing that thou could'ſt (or can'ſt) prove, to give two. Alas! <hi>Thomas,</hi> tho thou may'ſt account me poor or ſuch an inconſiderable perſon as thou ſay'ſt, thou art almoſt aſham'd to take notice of, (and indeed might be quite aſhamed ſo to be lye and abuſe me as thou haſt,) Yet I never, like thee, turned Informer againſt a Preacher, and told where he inhabited, and ſpread this Information as thou didſt (or cauſe to be done) the 14 of the 5 month, 1682. unto many People at <hi>Bull and Mouth, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore Oh! <hi>Tho.</hi> Repent (if thou can find a place) of thy wickedneſs, lyes, ſlanders, and hard ſpeeches againſt the Servants of the Lord, leave of being an Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and remember that <hi>Judas</hi> who informed againſt and betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Maſter, tho he got thirty peices of Silver thereby, yet he hanged himſelf. And <hi>Solomon ſaid true, A wicked doer giveth heed to falſe lips, and a lyar to a naughty tongue, Pro</hi> 17.4. And Rich &amp; proud <hi>Haman,</hi> who Informed againſt poor <hi>Mordecai</hi> (who it's like was as inconſiderable in his eye as I am in thine) was hanged on the ſame Gallows he prepared for poor <hi>Mordecai, for whoſo mocketh the poor reproacheth his maker, and he that is glad at calamities, ſhall not be unpuniſhed, Pro,</hi> 17, 5, And know the Lord is fulfilling his ſaying by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet, 13. Cap. 11. <hi>I will puniſh the world for their evil, and the wicked for their iniquity, and I will cauſe the Artogancy of the proud to ceaſe, and I will lay low the haughtineſs of the terrible.</hi> Therefore I ſay again, repent (if thou can'ſt find a place) of all thy lyes, ſlanders, defamations, &amp; thy envious fooliſh, and Impertinent ſcribling, againſt the Lord and his faithful People, for the <hi>Lord will utterly deſtroy the tongue of the Egyptian Sea, and every tongue that riſes up in judgment againſt him</hi> (in his faithful People) <hi>will he condemn, for the deſtruction of the tranſgreſſors and of the ſinners ſhall be together, and they that forſake the Lord ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31734:11"/>And no Weapon form'd againſt his heritage and ſervants ſhall proſper,</hi> for the Lord hath now exalted, and is more and more exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him (in his People) <hi>that ſhall judge with righteouſneſs, reprove with equity, and with the breath of his lips ſhall ſlay the wicked,</hi> whether Apoſtate, Innovator, Perſecutor, or Informer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Thomas</hi> thou ſeemeſt to be offended at the ſober &amp; Chriſtian Women-meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſcoffingly calls them <hi>G. F's.</hi> But as to them thy confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and contradiction concerning them is clearly manifeſted in <hi>Robert Sandilands</hi> Righteous judgments placed, <hi>&amp;c. Cap.</hi> 10. p. 100. to which I refer thee, and as for thee and the reſt of thy mind and companys talking againſt them in the words of good women, I thus adviſe and counſel you. Talk no more ſo exceeding proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, let not arrogancy proceed out of your mouth for the Lord is a God of knowledge, and by him actions are weighed. And of thee, Oh <hi>Thomas,</hi> it may be ſaid thou art weighed in a bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and found wanting of true Charity and Chriſtianity, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thy great pretences thereto. I have ſpent more time and paper then I intended to have done, in anſwer to thy envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, fooliſh, impertinent, <hi>Babels</hi> or babbles and with the words of the wiſeman ſhall conclude; <hi>Be not a witneſs againſt thy Neighbour without cauſe. And deceive not with thy lips, for there ſhall be no reward to the Evilman, and the candle of the wicked ſhall be put out, for their hearts ſtudieth deſtruction, and their lips talk of michief. Prov.</hi> 24.2 </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J.F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <p>IN the 6 part of <hi>T. C's. Babels,</hi> I take notice of that wherein I am notably noted, his two tranſcendent Epitheres to me <hi>[abominable, learn'd]</hi> By the rule of proportion of words ending in — able, taking <hi>[abominable]</hi> in an active ſignification; as <hi>[penetrable]</hi> able to pierce, as well as to be pierced. So firſt, by the way I am able to pierce through his abominably learned Rapſadoe of lyes, as having 4 errours in 8 Letters, which as a ſtrong word he ſets as a Baricado in the front, the firſt ſave one of his ſtrong lines, trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it in his firſt page; ſhewing his emulation or envy to others learning; and his aſpiring to his Maſters, <hi>Rogers</hi> and <hi>Bugg's</hi> learning. The learned Biſhop <hi>Hooper's</hi> learned tranſlators, (miſrendring his firſt word) and the learned vindicators of the controverted point.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>De Chriſtiana libertate,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſhew themſelves to be ſo unlearned. And alſo by the grace of God, I am made able to abominate Idols, their monuments and maintenance, which he accounts as an abomination in me as accounting Tythes the Popes Yoke.<note place="margin">J Sel. den. Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Tythes.</note> Though <hi>Alchuin</hi> our Country-man the learned founder of <hi>Paris</hi> Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, Schoolmaſter to the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the great, the great advancer of the Pope, and the maker of the firſt Law for his Tythes, diſſwaded the Emperour from laying the Yoke of Tythes on the Saxons. <hi>J. Selden</hi> Hiſtory of Tythes; there he may read them called a Yoke. So having anſwered a fool according to his folly to low his conceit; I need not trouble the Reader any further with it</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Richardſon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:31734:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
